<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great gospel sumonds, to close with Christ under the pain of the highest rebellion against the God of heaven, being the substance of a preface and sermon at Hemphlar-bank in the parish of Lanrick Feb. 20, 1676 / by Mr. John Welsh ...</title>
            <author>Welch, John, ca. 1624-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39037</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18206882</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18206882</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107104</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65421)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107104)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1136:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great gospel sumonds, to close with Christ under the pain of the highest rebellion against the God of heaven, being the substance of a preface and sermon at Hemphlar-bank in the parish of Lanrick Feb. 20, 1676 / by Mr. John Welsh ...</title>
                  <author>Welch, John, ca. 1624-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107104:1"/>
            <p>THE GREAT Goſpel SUMONDS TO CLOSE WITH CHRIST, Under the Pain of the Higheſt Rebellion againſt the GOD of Heaven; being the Subſtance of a <hi>PREFACE</hi> and <hi>SERMON</hi> at <hi>Hemphlar-bank</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Lanrick</hi> Feb. 20. 1676.</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>John Welſh</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Iron-Gray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But He was Wounded for our Tranſgreſſions, He was Bruiſed for our Iniquities: The Chaſtiſemens of our Peace was upon Him, and with His Stripes we are Healed.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:107104:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107104:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE</head>
            <head type="sub">The <hi>24</hi> Pſalm from the <hi>9</hi> Verſe being Sung.</head>
            <p>IF it be asked at us, as ſome will be ready to ask, by what Authority do ye theſe things? Who gave you this Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity? Ye have no Warrand neither from the <hi>King</hi> nor the <hi>Rulers</hi> for what ye have done: Wa, they have ſtraitly charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us to ſpeak no more in this <hi>Name.</hi> We Anſwer, we do it by the Authority of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> The Great Shepherd of the Flock, He has commanded us to Preach in Seaſon and out of Seaſon; He has given us Commandment to go and Preach and Baptize all Nations; and therefore they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden us that are in Power: But we muſt Anſwer as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle did, <hi>Is it fit in the Sight of GOD to Obey you or GOD, judge ye:</hi> He who is The <hi>King</hi> of <hi>kings,</hi> it is by Vertue of His Orders, <hi>Who is the Mighty GOD, The Judge of the whole World,</hi> before Whom we muſt all appear, He has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and it is by Vertue of His Command that we come to Preach, and it is by Vertue of His Command that ye come to Hear, and we will rather bide the Glooms of our <hi>Rulers,</hi> or we bide the Glooms of our <hi>GOD;</hi> We will rather take His Approbation, <hi>Well done thou Good and Faithfull Servant,</hi> than we will ſtudy to be called Unloyal, and yet we are very Loyal, Loyal we are, and Loyal we are commanded to be, but in Subordination to GOD, we muſt firſt <hi>Fear GOD and then Honor the King;</hi> but when the Command of the King juſtels with the Command of, GOD, then we are at a Point what is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107104:3"/>our preſent Duty: O for a blyth Meeting, and for the ſhining of his Preſence this Day: For we may put it as a great Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion if ever we will all Meet again; Yea we may put it out of queſtion that we will never all Meet again in this ſide of Time: And it is like that there are ſome here that ſhall Curſe the day that ever they were brought into the World. And O ſirs! It is a ſad thing that there ſhould be ſuch Grounds of Suſpicion of this amongſt you, that he lived where there was ſo much of a Powerfull Preached Goſpel, and under Lively Ordinances: But there is very much of this, and many ſtood in the Croſs Way when his People fled before his Enemies; If GOD be GOD they ſhall rew it: But we could wiſh that ſuch rewing might be in Time, and that they might prevent their utter Deſtruction: But we are afrayed many an one rew it when it is too late. It is a ſore Matter that Men ſhould be found not to Venture as far for JESUS CHRIST in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as they will Venture in the Service of a Mortal Man: Some has even Ventured very far in their Service that has got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten but little Thanks for it; Many has gotten ſore Wounds, and gotten ſmall Reward. But our LORD will not do ſo: There is never one can come and ſay to Him, I have gotten this Wound in your Service: There is never one that can come and ſay to Him, I have gotten this broken Head or this Wound in your Service, but they will be well Rewarded: None can ſay I have been Fyned or Confyned, or I have been put out of Houſe and Hold in your Service; Well ſays the LORD, <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ye into your Maſters Joy.</hi> There is none of you that has loſt a Cot-houſe for Him, but ye ſhall get a Kingdom, and then what will ye be behind: Therefore there is two Words that I ſhall tell you of that are here that are his People. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Have Courage and ſyd with his Ordinances and his Cauſe and Intereſt: Continue waiting upon thir Opportunities, and you may blame your ſelves and ye want them, for the matter is not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107104:3"/>without hope: No, no; Our <hi>LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> He will keep the Fields yet, <hi>and His Enemies ſhall be made His Footſtool:</hi> Therefore ſirs, <hi>wait on the LORD,</hi> as it is in the hinderend of the 27 Pſalm, that Pſalm that ye were ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Wait on the LORD and be of good Courage, and He ſhall ſtrengthen thine Heart: Wait I ſay upon the LORD:</hi> Chriſtians tyne not your Strength, for I aſſure you there is very many Great and Sweet Encouragements that your Labour ſhall not be forgotten, ye ſhall be well Rewarded, for all your Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are written in a Book. There is a Book, and the <hi>King</hi> will call for that Book, that it may be read, and will ſay, <hi>What ſhall be done to the Man that the King delighted to Honor?</hi> What ſhall be done to this Man that has Suffered, and has gotten no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, he ſhall be exalted and ſet above the reſt, and Honor and Reſpect ſhall be put upon him; Honor and Reſpect ſhall be put upon them that have had their Heads and their Hands put up upon Ports, and theſe that has had their Bodies burnt; and the <hi>LORD</hi> will fetch them in, and ſay, <hi>Thus ſhall it be done to the Man that the King delighteth to Honor.</hi> Wait on a while poor ſilly doubting troubled Soul, thats fleit for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrong about thy own particular Caſe, <hi>Wait on the LORD;</hi> He will ſatisfie poor Folk who ſits on the Throne of Grace: Wait upon Him, till he prepare his Anſwer to the queſtion: Wait upon him ye that are Sad and Weary, and Crying, <hi>Oh for my Mother, and for my Mothers Caſe!</hi> as it is in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, <hi>What will be done for Her in the day that She is ſpoken for?</hi> for there is few or none to do for her or to ſpeak for her, or to take her by the hand to lead her forth. Many Miniſters has left her, &amp; many Profeſſors has left her: <hi>What will we do for Breaſts to her?</hi> What loſs of Miniſters has She had? and what great loſs of Children has befallen Her? That is Sad ſays ſome: How dow we Wait? for his Work in particular is even ſore Diſtreſt; If it were not ſo, there would be ſome hope that we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107104:4"/>would have a Glorious and Beautifull Upſhot. Its twice there in the laſt Verſe of the 27 Pſalm, <hi>Wait ye;</hi> and he ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens his Argument (ſays he) <hi>I ſay upon the LORD.</hi> Its ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your Unbeliefs that makes you have no Patience to Ware upon the <hi>LORD</hi> as he has Commanded. Says many we may Wait long till our Eyes go Blind or we ſee Miniſters ſent to Preach the Goſpel; <hi>Wait upon the LORD, and be of good Cheer: Wait I ſay</hi> (ſays he) <hi>upon Him:</hi> For why? The LORD will not forſake his People; He will once have about with his Enemies, have about of his enemies, He will have about with them; He will once make them hing their Heads, and think Shame of Themſelves for what they have done. It may be that there is many here that deſires never to ſee that Day; It is like and it is like alſo, that there is ſome here may ſee that Day, that if the Queſtion were ſpeired would Anſwer, <hi>Lo this is our God and we have Waited for Him, and we will be Glad and Rejoyce in His Salvation:</hi> But there is even ſome Folk that has been Stout in Wronging <hi>CHRIST</hi> and his People. I ſay who knows how ſoon they may be put quite out of Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance with <hi>GOD</hi>'s Appearing; They will be ſaying in that Day, <hi>When ſaw we Thee Hungry and Fed Thee not? When ſaw we Thee in Priſon, and Viſited Thee not?</hi> They would fain deny every Ill Turn that they have done to his People; but it will not be with them.</p>
            <p>Sirs, I do not Grudge much that I ſee not many of theſe Folk that they call <hi>Gentils</hi> here; I ſhall never Repine at that which <hi>CHRIST</hi> Rejoyces in, <hi>I Thank Thee, O Father, who has Revealed theſe Things unto Babes.</hi> What is come of them all? There is never one of the Lords and Lairds and Great Men for Him: There is few of the Great Men (as ye call them) for Him: We hear little tell of their Religion that was the Carriers on of Religion, where are they all now? We man even tell them, that there are a whein poor People in the Land that are ſticking to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107104:4"/>Him; <hi>The poor of the People ſhall Truſt in Him,</hi> and there were no moe. And it is a great Mercy, GOD has taken a Sacrifice, and a Noble Sacrifice at the very firſt beginning: He took a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at the beginning, that Worthy Great-man the Merqueſs of <hi>Argyle;</hi> and he got a Miniſter too, to Seal his <hi>Covenant;</hi> and a very Worthy-man he got, a Gentleman, a very Eminent Conſiderable Gentleman <hi>Wariſton,</hi> that Worthy Gentleman he Dyed for the <hi>Covenant:</hi> He has taken one of all Ranks to Seal the <hi>Covenant</hi> and his <hi>Truths;</hi> and then after that, he took the <hi>Commons,</hi> he took many of them that were Poor Men, that he brought out and honoured them with Scaffolds, and gave Teſtimony for the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> of GOD: and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince that Day, there is ay ſome Body that follows him, and ay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Body that GOD takes Teſtimony from, ſome with Fyning, and ſome with Confyning, and ſome with impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Ye that is Young Ones, it may be, ye will ſpeir the Queſtion, Wherefore was it that all that was? and how came it that their Preachings was upon Hill-ſides, and that Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was? It may be the Days is coming it will be told: And we tell you it the Day from this Hill-ſide, it will be told, and the Young Ones will ſpeir, how could that be? (co the Bairns) Was that in <hi>Covenanted-Scotland?</hi> What was the Cauſe of this? There bude to be ſome Abominable Provoking Cauſe of this: And it will be Anſwered, It was even the Sins of his People that had provoked him; he gave them up to their Enemies, and they ſhut out all the <hi>Godly-Miniſters,</hi> and they ſent in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them a whein Wicked, Ungodly, Unconſcionable Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Men to fill up their Room, and the <hi>Godly</hi> were put to the Wilderneſs. Well, when the Time of Delivery comes, think ye not but it will be a fell Story to tell the Bairns off. O when our Stories is read, there will be uncouth Things in it to be read; and the very worſt of Men, how ready ſoever they be now to Perſecute, ſhall be made to drie their Shame; Their Shame ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107104:5"/>be from Generation to Generation, and their Poſterity ſhall think. Shame to ſay that ſuch a Man was my Qurcher, or ſuch a Man was my Grand-father. And it may be many of you no ſee that Day: We cannot tell, it may be ſo and other ways too GOD has done as great Things for us: And I aſſure you it may fall out ſo, that the LORD give his Enemies a dead ſtroak. Ay ſays Enemies, we never knew that GOD would have done ſuch a Thing. They ſay among the Heathen, <hi>the LORD has done Great Things for them:</hi> Ay ſays the People of GOD, ye ſee he has done Great Things for us whereof we are Glad. They had never mind of a Sorrowfull Day then that they had, they were all forgotten.</p>
            <p>Now we ſhall not detain you any longer: Let us go and call upon the LORD, that he would give us a Word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Time, and a Bleſſing. Let us Pray.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <head>FOLLOWS THE SERMON, Ye will find it written in the 53. of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> at the 5. Verſe.</head>
            <head type="sub">But He was wounded for our Tranſgreſſions; He was bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our Iniquities; the chaſtiſement of our Peace was upon Him, and with His Stripes we are Healed <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Find the moſt part of you a Company of Stupid Hearers: Our LORD may have Deſigns that we know not off; But for us, for ought we ſee, we may ſay, Why is this? Was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107104:5"/>it to go and Offer CHRIST to a Company of Careleſs Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that Cares not for Him, and that are not affected with the Offer; <hi>But His Thoughts are not like our Thoughts:</hi> He knows what his Deſign in this is.</p>
            <p>Well we have pitched upon this Scripture, as thinking that if any thing may readily affect your Hearts, and melt your ſtony Hearts within you, we may have ſome Purpoſes to ſpeak off that which may do it. O that GOD would help us, and that his Right Hand might be Revealed in this Preached Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Then the Words that we have read, take them up in theſe <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five</hi> Particulars: For the whole Story is of <hi>CHRIST and his Sufferings, and of a Covenant of Redemption be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Father and the Son,</hi> as ye may gather almoſt from every word of the Chapter, and the Perſons for whom he Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and what Caſe they were in; how little they could do for the getting of his Love manifeſted to them. So we have ſomewhat ſpoken of CHRIST, <hi>He was Wounded, He was Bruiſed, He Suffered. Secondly,</hi> Ye have ſomewhat ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Elect for whom CHRIST <hi>was Wounded and Bruiſed:</hi> What were they? <hi>They were Tranſgreſsors, they were Sinners, they were Men that were full of Diſeaſes, and Putrifying Sores. Thirdly,</hi> Ye have the Benefits, what they were that reſulted to theſe <hi>Elect Sinners</hi> by his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: There is two of them, they are mentioned in the words read; they are there mentioned <hi>Peace and Healing,</hi> Two Great Benefits. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Ye have how this comes to paſs; <hi>What made CHRIST to be Wounded? How came He to be Wounded?</hi> It was for <hi>Sinners,</hi> it was for a number of <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors,</hi> and that points at that which was the Eternal Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action between the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son,</hi> when they cloſed the Tranſaction concerning the Salvation of <hi>Sinners.</hi> The <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> requires the <hi>Son</hi> to Die: Says the <hi>Son,</hi> I undertake it: Therefore the <hi>Father</hi> keeps Him at his Undertakings, He will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107104:6"/>have the <hi>Son</hi> who entered <hi>Surety</hi> be as good as his Word, and He will have Him pay the Ranſom, and He will paſs it. <hi>He was Bruiſed for our Tranſgreſſions,</hi> that we might have Peace: <hi>He was Wounded for us,</hi> and therefore by <hi>his ſtripes</hi> we might be made Whole. But take the Words more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, There is Two Kinds of Perſons ſpoken of here, and there is ſomewhat ſpoken of the Two Kinds of Perſons. The Firſt Perſon ſpoken of is <hi>He,</hi> What He? <hi>The LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST the Fathers onely begotten Son, He who counted it no Robery to make Himſelf Equal with GOD: He who was filled with all the Fullneſs of the God-head: He that from all Eternity rested in the Boſom of the Father,</hi> it was <hi>He.</hi> The Second Perſon ſpoken of is, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> and <hi>We:</hi> Our Tranſgreſſions, and our Iniquities, <hi>we are healed.</hi> Who is this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> and <hi>We</hi> that is here ſpoken of? Its not all the World; but it is only them that CHRIST has purchaſed out of the World: It is not all Sinners, but <hi>us</hi> and <hi>we</hi> that is <hi>Poor E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected Perſons</hi> that the LORD has given Him of the Father to Seek and to Save, and that He has Undertaken to Save. Then, What were <hi>his Sufferings?</hi> and that is the Third-Thing, <hi>What were the Sufferings of our LORD JE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST that He <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakes?</hi> There is three words to expreſs this: <hi>He was Wounded,</hi> that is one; <hi>He was Bruiſed,</hi> that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of them; <hi>and He was Smitten,</hi> thats another word in the general. We ſee then from the whole Scope of the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of our LORD JESUS CHRIST that they were Very Great, and that there was no Worth in <hi>Poor Elect Sinners</hi> for whom he Suffered. What were they? They were ſuch as were <hi>Workers of Iniquity,</hi> ſuch as was <hi>very great Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,</hi> ſuch as was <hi>Rank Enemies to GOD,</hi> ſuch as were <hi>Woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of him,</hi> and that there was no <hi>Groſs Evil</hi> but they had the ſame Temptations too, that the reſt of the World follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Thoſe that had given him many a Wound; and there was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107104:6"/>nothing of odds between them and the reſt of the Wicked World. And then ye have what the <hi>Benefits</hi> were that he Purchaſed unto his People, and there is Two of them, <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Peace</hi> points at our <hi>Justification,</hi> and <hi>Healing</hi> points at our <hi>Sanctification</hi> And then Laſtly, How comes this that CHRIST ſhould ſuffer for <hi>me?</hi> How comes this to paſs? What could move JESUS CHRIST to be <hi>wounded?</hi> What moved him to undergo ſuch <hi>Great Sufferings</hi> and Sharp for <hi>Sinners?</hi> And this comes to be Anſwered by Vertue of the <hi>Covenant</hi> that paſt between <hi>Him</hi> and the <hi>Father,</hi> for the ſatisfying of the <hi>Divine Juſtice</hi> of GOD, that <hi>Poor Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> might not be deſtitute: <hi>Divine Justice</hi> muſt be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; and this <hi>Divine Justice</hi> is ſatisfied by <hi>his wounds</hi> and by <hi>his Chaſtiſements,</hi> and <hi>Stripes.</hi> So he ſatisfies for theſe things that <hi>Justice</hi> calls for from them, and ſo <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Mercy is made to kiſs one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I come to ſpeak to ſome few <hi>Doctrines,</hi> for we have here the Sum of the whole Goſpel: Therefore we wad have you thus taking notice, Firſt, <hi>We have Mans Miſery.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Ye have the Redeemer ſet out there.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Ye have a peace of Mans Redemption out of Miſery.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Ye have the Benefits and Purchaſe ſet out.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Ye have the Grounds of all this, the Covenant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then I have five Points of <hi>Doctrine</hi> to ſpeak a word ſhortly to from this that we have read, and we ſhall labour to keep with your ordinary time.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing then is this, <hi>That by Nature Elect Sinners als well as others, are in a very ſad and loſt Estate:</hi> Its not only the World that is here called thir <hi>Tranſgreſſors</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies;</hi> but it is even thoſe that the LORD has Choſen out of the World to ſave: I ſay that even the Elect People of GOD are by Nature lying in a very deplorable Condition: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſtands the Sadneſs of their Caſe? But we have oft had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107104:7"/>to ſpeak to it, and therefore we ſhall be but very ſhort on it; yet there is Three Things: There is Firſt, Mickle Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole Nature; and there is our Actual Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, whereby we are Defyled, Enemies to GOD, lyable to his Curſe and Wrath to all Eternity: This is the Caſe of all the <hi>Elect,</hi> Men and Women. There is no Ground then where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Sinner, that GOD has ſhewed Mercy upon has to boaſt of, if he look to the <hi>Rock from whence they are hewn.</hi> We will find it juſt our State that is the State of the Wicked World, that gets Hell to their hinderend: It is free Grace on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that has made the Change; for in our ſelves there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. Ille tell you Sirs, we ſhall leave the <hi>Application</hi> for the moſt part of all thir to the cloſe. Therefore the Second Point of <hi>Doctrine</hi> that I ſhall ſpeak to is this, <hi>That Our LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST the Son of GOD, the Second Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Trinity, He, for the Salvation of Loſt Sinners undertook many a Great Suffering:</hi> All thir Expreſſions holds out this, and we may ſafely found a <hi>Doctrine</hi> upon this word. Look to the whole Chapter and ye will ſee it clear for whom it is that he ſuffered, even the <hi>Elect World,</hi> CHRIST (ye ſee) ſuffered for them that gave him no Thanks; He ſuffered for them that helped on his Sufferings; <hi>he was deſpiſed, and counted ſmitten of GOD by them</hi> that thought nothing of him; <hi>they ſaw no Beauty nor Comlineſs in him;</hi> it was even for them that he ſuffered. I ſhall ſpeak more particularly to this <hi>Doctrine</hi> in thir Things, Firſt, <hi>I ſhall ſhew what Great Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings our LORD underwent for to bring healing and peace unto Sinners.</hi> Secondly, <hi>For whom it was he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went theſe Sufferings.</hi> Did our LORD undergo ſuch Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings for <hi>Sinners?</hi> To fall upon this were a very great head to ſpeak to, to tell you what he ſuffered in his <hi>Conception,</hi> and to tell you what he ſuffered when he was brought forth into the World in his <hi>Child-hood,</hi> to tell you what he ſuffered
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107104:7"/>before he entered upon <hi>his Publick Ministry,</hi> and to tell you what he ſuffered when he was taken and araigned, and brought before the Judgement-ſeat of <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilat,</hi> and Condemned; and to tell you what he ſuffered upon <hi>his Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and what he ſuffered upon <hi>his Soul:</hi> I ſay it would take very much Time, and we would but ſpill it in the ſpeaking too. And therefore I Recommend unto you the laſt Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> and the laſt Chapter of <hi>Luke,</hi> and the laſt Chapter of <hi>John,</hi> and unto that which is here recorded of him by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> ay but I ſhall tell you of ſome Things wherein his Sufferings appears to be <hi>very great,</hi> and we may judge by thir Things. (I pray you Sirs take heed) <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider what was the <hi>Debt</hi> that he undertook to pay, it was not the <hi>Debt</hi> of one or two, but even <hi>of the whole Elect,</hi> Men and Women, many Thouſands Millions of them, many Thouſands of them that cannot be counted, it was that which he ſuffered that they ſhould have ſuffered throw Eternity. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered <hi>Great Things:</hi> Wherefore? It was to ſatisfie the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Justice of GOD;</hi> The <hi>Divine Juſtice of GOD</hi> was put in Arms, and ſet againſt the <hi>Son</hi> for the Revenging of a <hi>broken Law,</hi> and a <hi>broken Covenant;</hi> and the <hi>Son of GOD</hi> had the <hi>Divine Juſtice</hi> of GOD to ſatisfie for the <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Actual Tranſgreſſions</hi> of the <hi>Elect,</hi> and for all the Breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the <hi>Commands</hi> of GOD, for that Mans breaking of this Command, and for this Mans breaking of that Command, and every Mans Sins that is moe than the Hairs of his Head for number. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Look to this and ye will ſee that it bud to be <hi>Great Sufferings</hi> he underwent; becauſe his Sufferings was as much to manifeſt a juſt GOD, as the Creation of a World did to manifoſt a Powerfull GOD, and an Almighty GOD: So that his Sufferings does as much to manifeſt a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull and Omnipotent and Juſt GOD. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Will ye conſider that theſe Sufferings behoved to be <hi>very Great Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings;</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:107104:8"/>For they were ſuch as put the <hi>Son of GOD</hi> ſo ſore to it, that it put him to a Strait, as it were, it put him to a Streſs like a Man indeed that was charged for a Great Sum; it put him to a Streſs, and to Pray; and ſo our LORD was put to ſuch a Streſs that he crys, <hi>now is my Soul troubled, and what ſhall I do?</hi> And he was put to pray to the <hi>Father.</hi> And then, <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Conſider this, How hard the Sufferings was that he undertook in particular, and ye will ſee that they were <hi>very many and great;</hi> Look to his Sufferings in his <hi>Incarnation,</hi> ye ſee he had not a Chamber to be brought forth in, he bud to be brought forth in a Stable; and he had not a Creedell, but a Horſe Mainger: And look to his Sufferings throw all his <hi>Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time,</hi> how many times he lay thereout at the back of a Buſh, and had but a Stone to lay his Head on; and how many times he was Hungry and Weary; and look to his Sorrow, what Grief of Mind he had, to ſee People crying out againſt him, juſt in the mideſt of his Sufferings; and to ſee <hi>Peter</hi> deny him even when he was Suffering for him; and look what he ſuffered in the <hi>Garden,</hi> when he drank that Cup that made him <hi>ſweat great Drops of Blood that came trinkling out of Him;</hi> and He had not only <hi>outward Sufferings</hi> but <hi>inward</hi> alſo, He was bearing the Wrath of GOD upon his <hi>Soul,</hi> that made Blood and Sweat come out of him, that made him to Faint that He dought not carry his own Croſs, but he bud to get help: and then look to his Sufferings what a <hi>Shamefull Death</hi> he was put to, what a <hi>Painfull Death,</hi> and what <hi>Travel of Soul</hi> he was put to, not only <hi>Travel in Body,</hi> but <hi>Travel in Soul,</hi> that made him cry out with Strong Crys and Tears unto Him that heard him, and he was made to Cry, <hi>My GOD, my GOD, Why haſt Thou forſaken Me?</hi> Now for whom was it that he ſuffered all this? Ye will ſee that and ye would look unto this ſame Chapter, and ye will read them for whom he ſuffered, it was even for <hi>many</hi> that had pierced and crucified him; <hi>for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107104:8"/>they ſhall look on Him whom they have pierced,</hi> Zech. 12.10. John 19.37. It was for them that gave him no Thanks for his Sufferings; He ſuffered for them that ſaid, it is well wared on him; He ſuffered for them that looked upon him as Deſpiſed and Rejected of Men; <hi>He was a Man of Sorrow, and acquainted with Grief,</hi> Iſaiah 53.3. For whom ſuffered he? Even for them that had Denyed him; and as the <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> turned their Back upon him, and killed him for them <hi>that Eſteemed Him not, Smitten and Wounded:</hi> It was even for them he ſuffered that were like Sheep going aſtray, it was for <hi>Sinners and Tranſgreſsors</hi> that he ſuffered all this; it was for a Company of Poor Men and Women that gave him no Thanks for his Sufferings, for they were ſo far from giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him Thanks, that they helped on his Sufferings, and ſome of them Denyed him to the adding to theſe Sufferings, <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Why was it that he ſuffered? We have ſpoken to that already, we ſhall only ſay but a word to it: <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is to tell you how holy a GOD he is, and how juſt a GOD he is, how faithfull he is in the Execution of his Threatnings, that he will not paſs by one Sin unpuniſhed, that ſpeaks out that he is <hi>Faithfull,</hi> &amp; that he would have his Threatnings faithfully Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, <hi>in that day thou eats thou ſhall ſurely die the death,</hi> Gen 2.17. He will have them fullfilled either in the <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal</hi> or in the <hi>Cautioner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of this, I ſhall leave it, becauſe I would ſain gain time. There is another <hi>Obſervation,</hi> and it is this, <hi>What are the Benefits that Redounds to us by His Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?</hi> What are the Benefits, There is Two mentioned here, <hi>Peace with GOD, and Healing to our Souls. What gets Sinners by his Sufferings? What get they?</hi> They get the Feid taken away that is between GOD and them, and they get <hi>healing to their Tranſgreſſions:</hi> They are not done away and his Blood purge them not away; we may be purged from all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107104:9"/>our Sins by his Blood: They muſt have Clean Water to Sprinkle them, and to Cleanſe them from all their <hi>Tranſgreſſions.</hi> He gives them <hi>Peace with GOD</hi> throw his Suffering, <hi>and Peace in their own Conſcience, everlaſting Peace in their own Conſciences; a Peace that paſſeth all Natural <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> There <hi>Peaces</hi> redounds to his People by his Sufferings.</p>
            <p>And then <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We have how <hi>his Sufferings</hi> comes to be brought about. How came it that the <hi>Juſtice of GOD</hi> falls upon him? and this leads us unto the Great Contrivance of the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> wherein this Matter was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived in the Counſel of GOD from all Eternity: In that he was to have a conſiderable part of Loſt Men and Women, and that he was to ſatisfie for them for a <hi>broken Covenant,</hi> and was to keep them from the <hi>Wrath of GOD,</hi> that was to come upon them by right for the breaking of his Law, and this was done by <hi>his Sufferings</hi> in their Nature for them.</p>
            <p>Now Sirs, I deſire this of you (that ye may be) now when I have brought Matters to this paſs, and given a touch of theſe Things; Then in order to the <hi>Application,</hi> Rouze up your ſelves to be ſuitably affected with what I have to ſpeak from thir Truths by way of <hi>Application:</hi> And there is thir Three <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> that I would make of it.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Firſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of <hi>Exhortation;</hi> We would Exhort you to be taken up with <hi>wondering,</hi> what Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is there among you that can hear thir Things ſpoken of, and no <hi>wonder</hi> at it? That CHRIST ſhould have ſuffered all this for the like of you and me; That He that is the <hi>Son of GOD</hi> ſhould have quat Heaven, and that the <hi>Son of GOD</hi> ſhould have become Man, that He ſhould have been put ſo ſore to it, as to Die for <hi>Sinners.</hi> We cannot tell what calls for <hi>wondering,</hi> and this calls not for <hi>wondering</hi> from us; <hi>O the height! O the bredth! O the length! O the depth of this Mystery!</hi> That the <hi>Son of GOD</hi> ſhould have been put ſo ſore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107104:9"/>to it as to die for <hi>Sinners;</hi> and not only to die, <hi>but to drink the Cup of the Fathers Wrath:</hi> Who can hear this declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and no <hi>wonder</hi> at the hearing of it; <hi>O wonder, O won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> at it Sirs! <hi>wonder</hi> at the hearing of it</p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall ſay this from it by way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Is it ſo, <hi>That our LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST was put to ſo Great Sufferings?</hi> Wa then I would Exhort you to look how ye ſhould look upon Sin, if sin ſhould not be very Deteſtable to you, and very abominable, if ye ſhould not be at very much Pains to forſake Sin that brought our Bleſſed LORD JESUS CHRIST to undergo ſuch <hi>Great Sufferings,</hi> which would have brought you to ſuch ſad Condemnation, and ly under the Wrath of GOD Eternally, and Eternally: And therefore <hi>Sinners,</hi> we think and there were no more to be a Motive to preſs you to forſake your Sins, and to hate every Falſe Way, and to hate the very leaſt Word and Thought of it, that this might be a Motive that it brought out LORD JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST to undergo ſuch <hi>Great Sufferings.</hi> Sirs, Love to Him will call for this, <hi>call ye that Love the LORD hate Evil,</hi> Pſalms 97.10.</p>
            <p>But then there is another <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> that I would make of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation Was our LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST brought to ſo many and Great Sufferings? and has be undergone them ſo cheerfully?</hi> Yea He has undergone it: And is He ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee the Travel of his Soul? O Sirs! Do not yet then do what ye can do to Diſappoint him, while he is making offer of his Blood to Waſh you: Do not that which will make him rew that he ſhed his Blood for the like of you: For when it is ſo, that ye do nor give him a ſuitable Meeting, ye give him juſt ground to rew; for ye have done what in you lyes to make <hi>his Sufferings</hi> of none Effect.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> that I ſhall mainly inſiſt on at this time, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Exhortation,</hi> and that is, <hi>Our LORD JE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107104:10"/>CHRIST is doing now, as he did after his Reſurrection, when he came out of the Grave, when his Diſciples ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in a Chamber for fear of the</hi> Jews, <hi>he came in there among them,</hi> and ſays, <hi>Peace be unto you,</hi> in that 20 of <hi>John</hi> 21 verſe, in the beginning of that Chapter there was ſome word of his Reſurrection: Now there was ſome of them that affirmed that he was riſen, yet ſtill they thought it was but a Notion and a Miſtake; although there was Angels come down from Heaven, and gave Teſtimony that He was riſen, yet ſome of them could not believe that; but when he comes in among them, What ſays he to <hi>Thomas?</hi> even that which he ſays to us the day, <hi>He holds out his Hands and the Hole that is in his Side, he ſhews forth his Hands, and his Side, and ſays, Be not Faithleſs but Believe, and that is the thing, reach hither your Hands into the Hole of my Side, and be not Faithleſs, but Believe;</hi> and that is the thing that I am come here for the day as a Meſſenger of the <hi>Living GOD,</hi> to let you ſee this Day the Wonderfull Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending Love of CHRIST, and to ſay unto you, <hi>Reach hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Hand of your Faith, and take a look of this Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Saviour who was Crucified, come put in your Fingers, put in your Hand in the Hole of that Bloody Side of his, and be not Faithleſs, but Believe:</hi> That is the <hi>Great Thing</hi> that <hi>CHRIST</hi> calls for, that is the <hi>Great End</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would have <hi>his Sufferings</hi> told us; Wherefore? That it might bring his People to a cloſe with Him, to give Him Credit, and to Believe in Him: Therefore now we come here, and that which we ſay to you, we bid you <hi>reach hither your hand, and be not Faithleſs, but Believe;</hi> that is the <hi>Great End</hi> wherefore he would have <hi>his Sufferings</hi> told, to cloſe with this Suffering LORD JESUS CHRIST: Come to him, and be no more <hi>Faithleſs, but Believe,</hi> and ſay with that Man <hi>Thomas, my Lord, and my God.</hi> Whenever that was preſented to him, he could no longer ſtand out: And this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107104:10"/>prevail not with you, I wonder what will prevail with you when the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of CHRIST is laid out unto you: Therefore ſays <hi>Thomas, my Lord and my God;</hi> I can ſtand no longer, <hi>for now I have ſeen the Wonderfull Love of GOD; now I ſee the Wonderfull Love of CHRIST, which made him undergo all theſe Great Sufferings; now I have ſeen the wonderfull excellency of a Saviour.</hi> Now therefore, Sirs, ye man give me leave to inſiſt here a little, for this is the Great Scope wherefore CHRIST keeps up a Preached Goſpel, that ye might believe, that ye may be ſaved, and brought to a Cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with JESUS CHRIST: Therefore, In the <hi>First</hi> Place, I do here <hi>ſummond</hi> you of all Ranks of Perſons unto a ſcrious Frame, and unto a Compoſure of Spirit ſuitable unto the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that I am to Declare unto you; I <hi>ſummond</hi> you Men and Women, and I come now to you, and I preſent before you, <hi>a Bloody CHRIST, a Suffering Saviour;</hi> I come to you as he did to his <hi>Diſciples:</hi> I ſay unto you as he ſaid to his <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Reach forth your hands unto a Bloody Saviour, take a look of him beleevingly;</hi> Look unto him, and Cloſe with him: Look to him who hath ſaid, <hi>Look unto Metall ye Ends of the Earth, and be ſaved,</hi> Iſaiah 45.22. O Sirs! Come and take a Look of this <hi>ſuffering</hi> CHRIST, take a Look of him: Therefore I ſhall <hi>Firſt</hi> tell what ſort of Perſons I <hi>ſummond;</hi> I <hi>ſummond</hi> you Old Perſons that has even had a Profeſſion all your Time, and yet never Cloſed with him, ye that has even made a faſhon of cloſing with JESUS CHRIST, and yet to this Day has never done it; I <hi>ſummond</hi> them at this Day at this preſent Time that they come and take a Look of this <hi>ſuffering</hi> JESUS CHRIST, that they ſtretch out the hand of their <hi>Faith</hi> and cloſe with him, and that they come and ſay, <hi>my Lord and my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I <hi>ſummond</hi> them that is without that has never yet been hankering about to do it, and them that has made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107104:11"/>Mints, but never came cleanly off in the doing of it; I <hi>ſummond</hi> you to come hither, <hi>and ſtretch out your hands, and be not Faithleſs, but Believe.</hi> I <hi>ſummond</hi> you Whoremongers, Adulterers, Drunkards, or whateve ye be, as ye heard in the Forenoon; come to him, O ſinners! come hither <hi>and reach hither your hands, and be not Faithleſs, but Believe,</hi> and cloſe with this <hi>ſuffering</hi> JESUS CHRIST; Will ye let him go away and not take the Offer off his hand? and he no get meikle Thanks for his Offer; Shall he have that to ſay, that ye would not take the Offer, and that ye would not give him meikle Thanks for <hi>his ſufferings?</hi> Will you not take the Benefits that he offers to you by <hi>his ſufferings?</hi> I come here in his Name, and offers you <hi>Peace,</hi> Will ye not take it? I offer you <hi>heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in his Name, Will you not take it off his hand?</p>
            <p>Now therefore there is <hi>Three Things</hi> that I ſhall ſhortly ſpeak to in this <hi>Exhortation,</hi> and I ſhall labour to contain my ſelf in als little bounds as I can in Proſecuting of it. Firſt, I ſhall ſpeak a word to this, <hi>after what manner we would have you cloſing with a ſuffering Chriſt,</hi> Secondly, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what Terms we would have you cloſing with a ſuffering Chriſt.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>From what Motives we preſs you to cloſe with a ſuffering Chriſt.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>We ſhall labour to ſatisfie the Objection of them that would go about this Work of cloſing with Chriſt.</hi> And then in the laſt Place, <hi>We ſhall require your Anſwer as to the Imbracing of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the <hi>Firſt</hi> Thing that we are to ſpeak to was, <hi>What way we are to cloſe with a ſuffering Chriſt:</hi> And there is <hi>Three Things</hi> in this cloſing with Him. <hi>Firſt,</hi> And ye wad cloſe with a <hi>ſuffering</hi> Chriſt. Ye muſt do it <hi>Timouſly,</hi> and ye muſt cloſe with him <hi>Inſtantly,</hi> at this very Time ye muſt cloſe with him: ye muſt not ſtand to conſider, and adviſe what he hath done for you, and what he hath ſuffered for you, and how that is that ye are made Partakers of his <hi>Benefits</hi> that he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107104:11"/>has purchaſed by <hi>his ſufferings. Secondly,</hi> Ye muſt Cloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with Him <hi>Deliberatly</hi> als well as <hi>Inſtantly;</hi> Ye may nor do it at Fits, a Braſh at it will not do the Turn: But it muſt be a Reſolved Buſineſs upon ſerious <hi>Deliberation;</hi> Ye muſt both do it <hi>Inſtantly</hi> and <hi>Adviſedly:</hi> I give you this Reaſon for it, becauſe I know, and ye come to Reſtrict your Cloſing with Him, and do it not <hi>Reſolutly</hi> and <hi>Deliberatly</hi> ye are fair to fall back again, and to turn your Backs upon Him when ye meet with the Croſs: Therefore it muſt be a thing done <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberatly.</hi> And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As ye muſt Cloſe with Him <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratly,</hi> ſo ye muſt not take CHRIST by Halfs, ye muſt take All CHRIST as He makes offer of Himſelf to be a <hi>King,</hi> and to be a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and to be a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and ye muſt take him for <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and for <hi>Sanctification;</hi> Ye muſt take him for a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> and for an <hi>Husband,</hi> to be a <hi>Guide,</hi> to be a <hi>Saviour</hi> and to be a <hi>Redeemer,</hi> to be <hi>all things</hi> that ye ſtand in need of, that is the Third Thing, ye muſt Cloſe <hi>Delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly.</hi> And then <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Ye muſt Cloſe with Him <hi>Cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> and ye muſt cloſe with Whole CHRIST, with your <hi>whole Soul;</hi> the <hi>whole Soul</hi> muſt give its Conſent: Ye muſt not cloſe with him with <hi>your Conſciences</hi> only, and with <hi>your Affections</hi> only; but ye muſt cloſe with him with <hi>your whole Soul:</hi> O what Great Advantage will ye have in cloſing with him <hi>Preſently.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then the next Thing that I Propoſed was, <hi>The Terms upon which ye are called to cloſe with Him;</hi> And for the Terms, I ſhall give you thir two or Three Words that holds out the <hi>Terms. Firſt,</hi> Ye will ſee it in the 55. of Iſaiah at the 7 Verſe. <hi>Let the Wicked forſake his Way, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Man his Thoughts, and let him Return to the LORD, and he will have Mercy, upon him, and to our GOD, for He will abundantly pardon:</hi> And ye will ſee another of them in the 3d of <hi>Hoſea</hi> at the 3d Verſe. There is one of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107104:12"/>
               <hi>Terms</hi> that we are called upon, <hi>Thou ſhalt abide for me for many days: Thou ſhalt not play the Harlot, and thou ſhalt not be for another, ſo alſo will I be for thee.</hi> Ye muſt abide for Him for many Days; Ye muſt not turn to other <hi>Lovers:</hi> Ye may not be like a <hi>Whoriſh-woman</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes <hi>Strangers:</hi> But ye muſt ſay, ye are Wedded to Him as <hi>your Husband,</hi> and ye muſt Prefer Him above <hi>all others.</hi> Ye may not turn to others, (ſays he) <hi>Ye must abide for me for many days.</hi> And then <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This is the <hi>Terms,</hi> Ye muſt cloſe with <hi>his Croſs;</hi> and ye would cloſe with him, ye muſt take <hi>Him and his Croſs.</hi> O Sirs! Ye muſt take <hi>Him and his Croſs,</hi> and any or you Reſolve to cloſe with Him, ye muſt alſo Reſolve to take <hi>Him with his Croſs,</hi> and to follow <hi>him whitherſoever he goeth, and to ſell all that ye may follow him.</hi> And that is the <hi>Terms</hi> in the 45 Pſalm at the 10 Verſe. <hi>Hearken, O Daughter, and Conſider, and Incline thine Ear; forget alſo thy own People, and thy Fathers Houſe, ſo ſhall the King greatly deſire thy Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the next Thing that I am to ſpeak to, is the <hi>Motives</hi> upon which we would have you preſſed to cloſe with Him: Now Sirs, May not this be a Reaſon for to move you to cloſe with him, the <hi>Great Benefits</hi> that he has purchaſed to them that will cloſe with him, both <hi>Peace and Healing,</hi> and this prevail not with you, we wat not what will prevail with you, O Sirs, Shall we go away and leave you this Day? Dear Friends, we dow not leave you untill we preſs you with thir <hi>Motives</hi> to cloſe with JESUS CHRIST; We would fain deal with you to cloſe with him, ye ſhall both get <hi>Peace</hi> &amp; <hi>Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in Time, and <hi>Peace</hi> after Time: Ye ſhall get <hi>Peace with GOD, and Peace with your own Conſciences;</hi> Ye ſhall get <hi>Peace to your own Souls;</hi> Ye ſhall get <hi>Perfect Peace; That Man ſhall be keeped in perfect Peace whoſe Mind is ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Him,</hi> Why? Becauſe He has purchaſed that to them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107104:12"/>that will cloſe with him; Ye ſhall get <hi>Peace and Healing:</hi> Poor Backſliden Sinners, that thinks ſhame of your Back ſlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: Hard hearted Sinners, that thinks ſhame of your hard heartedneſs, will you come to him, and cloſe with JESUS CHRIST, and take his Purchaſe that he has purchaſed with <hi>thir Wounds,</hi> and ye would come and cloſe with him ye ſhall get <hi>healing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then I come to ſome <hi>Motives</hi> out of the Text, And <hi>First,</hi> I ake this for a <hi>Motive,</hi> therefore ſirs, under the Pain of Rebellion as ye would not be found <hi>Traitors</hi> and <hi>Rebels</hi> to the <hi>Great GOD of Heaven,</hi> ye muſt cloſe with him. <hi>This is his Command that ye Believe on the onely Begotten Son of GOD:</hi> Therefore he Coimmands, and we Command and Charge you in his <hi>Name,</hi> under the Pain of <hi>Eternal Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;</hi> We Command you under the Pain of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Pain of being found <hi>Diſobeyers</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and under the Pain of all the <hi>Puniſhments</hi> that ſhall come upon you to cloſe with JESUS CHRIST. And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Cloſe with him, becauſe he is a GOD that is greatly ſatisfied to have <hi>his Benefits</hi> that he has purchaſed applyed to <hi>Sinners</hi> to have them making Application of them by cloſing with him, and ye would give him Satisfaction for <hi>his Benefits,</hi> and as ye would be carefull to ſatisfie him for them that is making Offer of them, this is the Way to ſatisfie him, to cloſe with him. And then <hi>Fourthly.</hi> Ye have many <hi>Calls</hi> to call you: I tell you ſirs, Ye are called by your frequent <hi>Sick-beds, Sickneſs</hi> in <hi>your Perſons,</hi> and <hi>Sickneſs</hi> in <hi>your Families,</hi> all theſe things is calling you: The <hi>Mercies</hi> of GOD is calling you; The <hi>Judgements</hi> of GOD is calling you; and ye have the <hi>Torments</hi> of <hi>Hell</hi> calling you; Ye have <hi>your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving Sinfull Hearts</hi> calling you, <hi>your Backſliden Hearts</hi> calling you. What then Sirs? Will ye not give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>your Luſt</hi> and cloſe with him, and imbrace him? Ye have the <hi>Angels</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:107104:13"/>calling you; Its ſaid that the <hi>Angels they rejoyce at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of one Soul:</hi> And ye have the <hi>Devil</hi> by all his <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> calling you; ſo ye have many <hi>Calls</hi> to cloſe with this <hi>Suffering</hi> LORD JESUS CHRIST. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Cloſe with him. Why? Becauſe he takes it as a great Proof of <hi>your Sincerity,</hi> even when once ye begin to ſay, <hi>My Lord and my God:</hi> Therefore cloſe with him; and then I would have you cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, <hi>as ye would not be found Guilty of Trampling <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder foot the Blood of the Covenant, and counting it an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nholy Thing;</hi> Even that <hi>Blood</hi> by which <hi>Sinners</hi> are to be ſaved.</p>
            <p>But now I come to the <hi>Laſt Thing</hi> that I propoſed, and that is, To ſpeir what ye have to ſay to it; What ſay ye to it? Have ye any thing to ſay againſt what we have been ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you? Have ye any thing to ſay againſt what <hi>He ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> Of againſt what he did after <hi>He ſuffered?</hi> When he ſaid <hi>Thrust in your hands in my Side, and be not Faithleſs but Believing?</hi> Or will ye be like <hi>Thomas</hi> after he had gart him ſee him, he crys, <hi>My Lord and my God.</hi> Well Sirs, What will ye all do? Tell me what ye think of all that has been ſaid <hi>of a Suffering</hi> CHRIST this Day? What Effect has it now upon you? And what Effect ſhall it have afterwards? Will ye leave this Place without Cloſing with JESUS CHRIST: What ſay ye to it? What ſay ye? Have ye any <hi>Objections?</hi> Yes ſays ſome, I have Three <hi>Objections.</hi> What is theſe <hi>Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> that hinders me. I have many Doubts in my Boſom, that I dar not preſume. Wherefore dar ye not? <hi>I have been ſuch a Great Sinner.</hi> I tell you then <hi>Sinners</hi> in the Name of the LORD, ye that have theſe Fears and Doubts, come away, and let not that hinder you; but let it put you to make the more uſe of the <hi>Maſter;</hi> Come away to Him, <hi>Though your Sins were as Scarlet and as Crimſon, ye ſhall be made White as Snow;</hi> in that firſt of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 18. verſe. Therefore let none
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107104:13"/>ſpeak that He is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwilling,</hi> He is not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwilling</hi> to help any of the <hi>Elect</hi> for whom he ſuffered ſo many things: I ſay never think that ye have that of your ſelves, and that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to <hi>Free-will</hi> (as the <hi>Blaſphemous Quakers</hi> ſays) ye have GODs Command for it, and ye have GODs Warrand for it, and ye have GODs Intimation, and theſe are his Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Duties that he bids you do. But what will ye ſay further: What ſhall I do? Let me ſee what I ſhall do. Be ſerious in going about that which you have Revealed in the Word of GOD to be your Duty, and that is all that the Goſpel calls for, and that you cloſe with JESUS CHRIST. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Say ye, I would fain cloſe with him, <hi>but I fear I break to Him again;</hi> this ye had ſpoken to in the forenoon. I have cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him, <hi>but I have broken again, and I never ingage in that Duty, but I break in ſome thing; I never put my hand to that, but I am croſſed in it.</hi> I like you all that ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that, that it is ſo; Reſolve in CHRISTs ſtrength, and he will keep you, and all the Devils in Hell ſhall not get you to break it. O! but ſay ye, <hi>I have been tryſted to make many Promiſes, and I have broken them all, and I fear that I do ſo again.</hi> I ſay, ye muſt Reſolve again in CHRISTs ſtrength; and the hand of <hi>Zerubabel</hi> that hath laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, he ſhall finiſh it. Go not from this Place till you cloſe with him; We dow not leave you till ye give your Conſent: <hi>Turn again unto Me,</hi> ſaith the LORD, <hi>and I will Heal your Backſlidings.</hi> Well Sirs, What have ye more for your Diſcouragements? Will ye come and Cloſe with him; He hath ſent me this Day to bid you come and Cloſe with Him, He who hath ſtopped ſo low as to make Offer of Himſelf to <hi>Sinners,</hi> and has undergone ſuch <hi>Great Sufferings:</hi> It ſhall be counted the <hi>Greatest Rebellion</hi> againſt The GOD that made you that can be done, when he has done all this to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe <hi>Salvation,</hi> and has brought it to your hands. (I pray
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107104:14"/>you Sirs, ſit down there, or I will ſpeak no more) and ye would not take it.</p>
            <p>But there is a ſecond <hi>Objection:</hi> Says ſome, <hi>I cannot cloſe with him; ye bid us cloſe with him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut we cannot it is als far from us as to touch theſe Skyes, we call do nothing in it</hi> Wa, What ſays the LORD to that Poor Man that had the <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered hand?</hi> He bids him <hi>ſtretch it out,</hi> I cannot wad he ſay; but yet what ſays the LORD to him? <hi>Stretch out thy hand.</hi> And we bid you in <hi>his Name</hi> make a Mint, and ſhew your Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d he will help you to do it, and ye would but make a Mint at it, and ye would but ſay <hi>LORD<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I believe with the Faith that I have, and as I can, I believe, LORD, help my unbelief.</hi> Its a ſtrange matter Sirs, ye will not try: The Man might have ſaid <hi>What needs me ſtretch but my wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered hand? I ken that I cannot stretch it out:</hi> But yet CHRIST bids him ſtretch it out as he can, and he makes his Mint Effectual. Ye that ſays ye cannot do ſo meikle as to make a Mint, make the Mint, and GOD will make theſe Mints Effectual. Ye that ſays ye cannot do ſo meikle as to make a Mint, make the Mint, and GOD will make theſe Mints Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, and ye may find him: And therefore, and ye dar not, or think ye ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>not get Grips of Him, yet will ye give Him a Look, <hi>Look unto Me all ye Ends of the Earth, and be ſaved,</hi> Iſaiah 45.22. <hi>For I am GOD, and there is none elſe.</hi> This is all that he requires, that ye would give him a Look.</p>
            <p>Well, What have ye to ſay in the <hi>Third</hi> Place. <hi>I will not cloſe with him, that is the Truth of the Matter; I will not part with the World; I will not Serve Him; I will not Obey his Commands; I am not Reſolved upon that yet; I will not leave the World that I have had ſo meikle Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in; no, no, I will not cloſe with him, let you ſay what you will.</hi> Woes me, that is a ſore Matter, will ye
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107104:14"/>not have him? Let Miniſters ſay what they will, will ye not have him? Whats the Reaſon or that? Have ye any thing to ſay againſt him? He is able to declare of himelf that it is not his fauit that makes you <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwilling.</hi> O ſay ye. <hi>He is a hard Maſter, there is no Living with Him, I will not get my Idols entertained in his Service; He is an uncouth hard Maſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there is no Living with Him, and I dow not part with my Idols my Luſts, and with my Sin; and ye would have the plain truth of it, I think there is neither Man nor Wife that ever has a blyth day in his Service, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt take my hazard, whatever come on the back of it, I must Sin, and I must take mine Advantage in theſe things.</hi> Well Sirs, I ſay there is meikle more Advantage to be had in cloſing with CHRIST, &amp; I ſhall ſay but Two Things to this: <hi>First,</hi> He will get better nor ever ſtood on your feet to ſerve him, and them that will be blyth of him, and that will be both ſeen and heard. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I tell you that he is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Good <hi>Master;</hi> but the Reaſon why ye do not believe, ye know not the heartſom hours in ſecret the People of GOD hath with him. Ye do not believe, but becauſe ye heard thir things ſpoken to already: I ſhall forbear, and ſpeak only to a word, and ſo I have done.</p>
            <p>Sirs, I think that we have met with a ſtrange piece of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, I cannot tell what it means, for we deſigned to have ſpoken the LORDs Word elſe where this Day; but we have beyond our Expectation b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en brought here again, and I would fain think that the LORD had done it, for ſome Deſign that he had for catching of ſome Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to himſelf, or at leaſt it is to make many inexcuſable in the Great Day: Well its by chance that we are brought here, I ſay this Day; and I have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting unto you, <hi>a bloody, wounded, and bruiſed CHRIST.</hi> O he is all Cruſhed with the <hi>Wrath of GOD:</hi> He was forced to cry, <hi>What ſhall I do? My Soul is Sorrowfull even unto
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107104:15"/>Death, and what ſhall I do?</hi> This <hi>Wounded CHRIST</hi> He has purchaſed Sarvation unto Sinners, and hath ſent us here this Day as his Ambaſſadors to make Offer of him, and we have been telling you of the <hi>Terms.</hi> Have we prevailed with you Sirs? What ſay ye to it? We are come in <hi>his Name</hi> and we may not leave you like a Knotleſs-threed; but as I am an Ambaſſador and Meſſenger of the <hi>Great King,</hi> and therefore I dar not leave you: Here is my Warrand, we are his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and here is my Blaze upon my Breaſt; We are his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, we come forth in the <hi>Kings Great Name; He who is KING of kings</hi> that made Heaven and Earth; and He by whom they ſhall be judged one Day: It is in <hi>his Name</hi> that we come forth; And I <hi>Summond</hi> and <hi>Charge</hi> you all, as ye will Anſwer before The <hi>Great GOD,</hi> and as ye would be found of Him in Peace, &amp; as ye would one Day look him in the Face, <hi>and no cry Hills and Mountains fall upon you</hi> to cloſe with him. We <hi>Charge</hi> you by the <hi>Love of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> that put him to ſuffer all theſe Things. <hi>Secondly,</hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> you by the <hi>Torments of Hell</hi> that ſurely ſhall follow upon Diſobeyers. We <hi>Charge</hi> you under the pain <hi>of ſuffering the Wrath of the Everlaſting GOD,</hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Obtest</hi> you by the <hi>Love of Him who was Dead and is now Alive, and Lives for evermore</hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> you by Him <hi>who hath the Keys of Hell and Death, and the Keys of Heaven.</hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> you that ye come and tell us, what ye Reſolve to do; or are ye Reſolved to live as ye have done? <hi>Are ye Prayer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, Godleſs Livers? Will ye leave off that? Are ye Drunkards? Will ye leave off that? Will ye yet Drink more? What Reſolve ye to do? Are ye Swearers? Will ye yet ſwear more? Are ye Repenting? Or Reſolve ye to live a while longer in your Sins? Will ye continue in theſe things, and keep your Idols, and your Corruptions? Are ye Reſolved upon that, or upon the other hand? Will ye
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107104:15"/>come this Day and make a Reſignation of all your Select unto the LORD,</hi> and cloſe with this <hi>Suffering CHRIST,</hi> before his Wrath come upon you. <hi>Have ye drawn buck will ye draw back more? Or will ye come to Him?</hi> We ſay Sirs, for our part, we are but Men, and it may be ſome of you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeen our Infirmities: But we come this Day in CHRISTs ſtoom; We are come here in <hi>his Name</hi> at this Time, and by <hi>his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Authority:</hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> you to come and Cloſe with JESUS CHRIST upon <hi>his own Terms. What ſay ye to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> your Conſciences that ye come and Cloſe with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> We <hi>Charge</hi> you under the <hi>Pain of Death.</hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> you under the <hi>Pain of the Higheſt Rebellion.</hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> you under the <hi>Pain of the Juſt Vengeance of GOD.</hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> you under the <hi>Pain of the Indignation of that Wrath that ſhall come upon Rebels</hi> to Cloſe with this <hi>Bloody Saviour JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST. What ſay ye to it?</hi> We <hi>Charge</hi> you to it: We Offer Him to you: We lay the Offer to every Mans Door, &amp; to every Mans Conſcience, &amp; we <hi>Command</hi> &amp; <hi>Charge</hi> you to come and Cloſe with Him: And we deſire the LORD GOD of Heaven that he would confirm this Argument; And if ye will not cloſe with him, he will make every Mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſtand as a Thouſand Witneſſes againſt him in the <hi>Great Day</hi> that Neglects this Offer, that Deſpiſes and makes Light of it. <hi>Now what ſay ye to it. Men and Women that has had many Preachings preached to you?</hi> We think its very like and GOD had ſent this Preaching to ſome Places of the Land where there is not ſo great a Profeſſion of Religion, we would not have gotten heard what we had been ſaying, there would have been ſuch a din amongſt them. O that Groſneſs of the Hearts of Siners that makes Light of this Great Offer! <hi>What ſay ye to it?</hi> We intreat you, we beſeech you to give an Anſweer. Say to it; We muſt have an Anſwer, and we deſire not to take a Denyal: No, no, thats no the Anſwer
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107104:16"/>
               <hi>that ye will not do it.</hi> We man have another Anſwer from you: For we are ſent to be Peremptor with you this Day; And we <hi>Charge</hi> you to come and take Him, and cloſe with Him this Day; For ye cannot tell if ever ye ſhall have the Offer again after this Day the 20. day of <hi>February.</hi> We ſay we cannot tell if ever we ſhall have the Opportunity to ſpeak to you again after this Day. What think ye Sirs, that it is for nought that we come out to Preach when we are in ſuch hazard, and when we are looked on as <hi>Traitors</hi> and <hi>Rebels</hi> in every one of thir Meetings; its not a ſmall Buſineſs this: Therefore GOD calls us to be Serious, and no to Trifle it, till we get our Buſineſs done. And therefore Men and Women will you come and cloſe with him. Dear Friends, will ye ſay to it: Dear Beloved Friends, will you let CHRISTs Death and Pains he underwent in <hi>his Sufferings</hi> per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wade you to take CHRISTs Offer: For we wound fain have you to cloſe with him, for your own Life and Salvation; we pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s it upon you, and as he is offered, ſo take him. Ye man prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e this, ſay to it. <hi>What ſay ye to it?</hi> Say to it, Dear Friends, give your Anſwer; ſay to it. <hi>What ſay ye to it?</hi> Say to him, we ſeek not your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Say to him, ſay ſomething to the LORD: For as the LORD lives ye man ſay ſomething, yea, or nay. <hi>What ſay ye to him?</hi> Cloſe with him, or as the LORD lives (I ſay) ye ſhall Curſe the Time that ye came here to all Eternity, for Refuſing CHRIST this Day in his Offer: Therefore ſpeak to GOD this Day as ye would not have him to ſpeak in Wrath to you Sirs, ſay <hi>that ye will be the LORDs</hi> Say, <hi>that ye will enter into as Everlaſting Covenant with Him never to be forgotten; or as the LORD Lives, theſe Stocks, and this Water, and that Brae, and the Earth that ye ſit on ſhall he a Witneſs againſt you, and this Tent and I, and theſe Clouds that is above your Heads ſhall be a Witneſs againſt you Eternally.</hi> Therefore now Sirs, come, and take the Of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107104:16"/>fer, and tell GOD that from this Day forward ye Reſolve to be for Him. Say to it: <hi>What ſay ye?</hi> Think ye that it is for nought that we come out upon ſuch a Buſineſs, and ſpend, the Lives in the Diſcharging of our Commiſſion. We are Diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to come here; but it is for your Immortal Souls that we are come here: Therefore in the <hi>Name</hi> of The LORD JESUS CHRIST, We <hi>Charge</hi> you, let it be your Work to cloſe with him. Say Sirs; <hi>What ſay ye to it?</hi> Say Old-men, &amp; Young-men, with ye cloſe with him Say Young-bairns, the Youngeſt of you all, will ye cloſe with him? Say to it, LORD, I would be content to cloſe with him? I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ye will not, then the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> ſhall be a Witneſs againſt you. Will ye ſpeak to him: Will ye caſt away your <hi>Idols,</hi> and ſay, <hi>What have I to do with Idols any more?</hi> Will ye ſay ſo Sirs. <hi>Now I betake my ſelf to him, he ſhall be my GOD, and I reſolve that it ſhall be ſo that he ſhall be my GOD and my King:</hi> Say ſo Sirs. Will ye ſay Old-men and Young-men? Will ye ſay Old-women and Young-women? Say to it: Anſwer GOD who is biding you cloſe with him: Say with Good <hi>David, Thou art my GOD and my King; for Thou haſt Eſtabliſhed my Throne, and put a Crown upon my Head; and He hath made with me an Everlasting Covenant well ordered in all things and ſure:</hi> He found him to be a Saviour when he was quite loſt. Well them, will ye ſay to it Sirs, we are but Fool Creatures, Poor Sinfull Men like your ſelves, and it may be ſometimes ye have ſeen our Weakneſs: But we ſay we are come here this Day not in our own Strength: But we tell you we are come here Cloathed with His Authority at this Time: We are not come here this Day in our own Name, but in the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of our <hi>Master,</hi> as we are Ambaſſadors of JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST, we beſeech you to cloſe with Him: We would fain fall down upon our Knees and that would prevail with you to gar you ſay the thing: We would fall down upon our bare
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107104:17"/>Knees before you. O Sirs, ſay to it: <hi>What ſhould you ſay?</hi> Say even that Word which <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaid, <hi>My Lord and my God;</hi> and ſay with <hi>David, O my Soul, though eſt ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord that thou art my God:</hi> But I ſaid moreover the Lord ſhall be my God. Say with the Church in that 50 of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and 5. verſe What is that, <hi>Come ſay they, let us enter our ſelves into an Everlaſting Covenant with GOD which ſhalt never be forgotten.</hi> Well Sirs, I ſay this Day ye muſt either enter into an Everlaſting Covenant with Him never to be forgotten. We man even leave you Sirs, and we dow not think of leaving till ye come to a cloſe with Him; Is there any here that will not Cloſe with Him? We fear that this be the <hi>Ill Turn</hi> that we were ſpeaking of in the Morning; Without queſtion the Word will be <hi>the Savour of Death unto Death to ſome, als well as it will be the Savour of Life unto Life unto others.</hi> Well Sirs, take heed what ye are Doing, go to Him, and Cloſe with Him. We would fain have you Cloſing with Him: I would think it Heartſom if there were many of you going alone, and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how it is with you every one of you; Try your ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, <hi>and the LORD perſwade you ſo to do;</hi> To Him be Praiſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107104:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
